Guide to the Darrin Zammit Lupi photojournalism archive, 2004-2017 RL.11613
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Darrin Zammit Lupi photojournalism archive
2004-2017
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lupi, Darrin Zammit
Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
RL.11613
3.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes 40 photographic prints 20x24 inches
29.3 Gigabytes 5031 files
Darrin Zammit Lupi is a photojournalist based in Malta. This archive comprises two bodies of documentary work. The earlier project, Malta Detention, consists of color photographs, taken by Lupi from 2004-2013, of African migrants and asylum seekers in Malta detention camps. In these camps, the migrants faced many months in limbo, waiting for the outcome of their journey and holding protests about their treatment. This series includes over 1800 digital files containing low-resolution images, contact sheets, and a group of news articles. The second project, On Board the MV Aquarius, comprises color photographs and supporting image files, documents, data, videos, news stories, and interviews compiled by Lupi in December, 2017, while on board the Aquarius, a migrant search and rescue ship operated by the non-profit organizations SOS Méditerranée and Médecins sans frontières; while there, he documented the rescue of 320 migrants in the Mediterranean Sea, and their safe arrival in Pozzallo, Sicily. All prints measure 20x24 inches. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
40 color photographic prints; 5033 digital files (4681 jpeg, 257 tiff, 68 png, 11 mp4, 10 pdf, 2 doc, 1 xls, 1 VLC, 2 txt)
Materials are chiefly in English, with a few in French, Italian, Korean, Spanish, and other languages.
Biographical / Historical
Darrin Zammit Lupi was born in Malta in 1968. He started his photography career with The Malta Independent in 1992, but decided to turn freelance shortly afterwards. He has documented conditions in Albania and the former Yugoslavia, the South-East Asia tsunami tragedy, the refugee crisis during the war in Kosovo, the earthquake in L'Aquila, Italy, and the war in Libya.
He has won the Malta Journalism Awards for Press Photography seven times and the Sport Photography award three times, as well as a special award for Creativity in Photojournalism. The Societies for Photographers in the UK named him Overall Photographer of the Year for 2016, Media Photographer of the Year for 2013, Documentary Photographer of the Year for 2014, and Street Photographer of the Year for 2016.
His work for Reuters has been published in newspapers, magazines, books and online worldwide. He holds a Masters Degree with Distinction in Photojournalism and Documentary Photography from the University of the Arts, London.
In late 2014, he published his book Isle Landers, covering a decade's work on irregular immigration and asylum seekers in the Mediterranean. Work from that collection has been exhibited in Malta, France, Luxembourg, and Australia.
Some of his works form part of the permanent collection at the National Museum of Fine Arts in Malta, private collections in other countries, and the Human Rights Archive at Duke University's David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Source: adapted from photographer's website, accessed Nov. 15, 2019)
Conditions Governing Access
Collection contains electronic records that must be requested through the collection guide and accessed in the Rubenstein Library reading room. Note: Tiff images from the "On Board the Aquarius" project are immediately available through links in this collection guide.
Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Darrin Zammit Lupi photojournalism archive was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2018 and 2019.
Scope and Contents
The Darrin Zammit Lupi photojournalism archive comprises two bodies of documentary work. The earlier project, Malta Detention, consists of color photographs, taken by Zammit Lupi from 2004-2013, of African migrants and asylum seekers in Malta detention camps. In these camps, the migrants faced many months in limbo, waiting for the outcome of their journey and holding protests about their treatment. This series includes over 1800 digital files containing low-resolution images, contact sheets, and a group of news articles. The second project, On Board the MV Aquarius, comprises 20 color photographs and over 4000 supporting image files, documents, data, videos, news stories, and interviews compiled by Lupi in December, 2017, while on board the Aquarius, a migrant search and rescue ship operated by the non-profit organizations SOS Méditerranée and Médecins sans frontières; while there, he documented the rescue of 320 migrants on boats in the Mediterranean Sea, and their safe arrival in Pozzallo, Sicily. All prints measure 20x24 inches.
Electronic resources related to these two projects include almost 5000 born-digital image files in tiff, jpeg, and png formats. These include digital contact sheets and low-resolution files, as well as full color tiffs from which images were chosen for printing. Note: Tiff images from the "On Board the Aquarius" project are available through links in this collection guide. All other electronic files must be requested in advance and are accessible only onsite in the library reading room.
The 2017 Aquarius migrant rescue project include many additional related digital files: these include nine videos in mp4 format, taken by Darrin Zammit Lupi. Five document the MV Aquarius rescue and a transfer of refugees from another ship; three are interviews with an Italian rescuer and two migrants; and one is a news report video narrated by Lupi. The interviews describe conditions in detention centers in Libya and on board the escape boats.
Other supporting documents and digital content for the 2017 Aquarius migrant project comprise press releases in English, French, Spanish, Italian, Korean, and other languages; shot lists; demographic data summarizing the makeup of the migrants on board the rescue ship; screen shots of Reuters social media posts relating to this story, featuring Zammit Lupi's images; and scans of a 17-page journal kept by Zammit Lupi while aboard the rescue ship.
All image titles, captions, and other descriptions have been taken from the originals.
Alien detention centers -- Photographs; Boat people -- Mediterranean Region; Human rights -- Mediterranean Region; Human trafficking; Humanitarian assistance -- Mediterranean Region; Photography of immigrants -- Mediterranean Region; Photojournalism -- Mediterranean Region; Photojournalists -- Mediterranean Region; Refuge (Humanitarian assistance) -- Italy; Refugees -- Mediterranean Region -- Portraits; Rescues -- Photographs; Africa -- Emigration and immigration; Italy -- Emigration and immigration; Malta -- Emigration and immigration; Malta -- Photographs; Mediterranean Region -- Photographs; Sicily (Italy) -- Photographs; Color prints (photographs); Contact sheets; Digital images; Digital moving image formats; Digital prints; Electronic documents; Inkjet prints; Journals; Lupi, Darrin Zammit; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); SOS Méditeranée; Médecins sans frontières (Association)
- On Board the Aquarius, 2017 December 15-19; 1.5 Linear Feet 1 box 20 photographic prints; 16.73 Gigabytes 3210 files (110 tiff, 3035 jpg, 46 png, 11 mp4, 3 pdf, 2 doc, 1 VLC, 1 txt, and 1 xls)
  Scope and Contents
  This body of work comprises several thousand documentary images and supporting documents, data, videos, news stories, and interviews from the project On Board the MV Aquarius, December 2017, by photojournalist Darrin Zammit Lupi, on assignment for the Reuters news agency. While on board the Aquarius, a migrant search and rescue ship operated by the non-profit organizations SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans frontières, Zammit Lupi witnessed and documented the rescue of 320 migrants in the central Mediterranean, and their safe arrival in Pozzallo, Sicily.
  Image formats include 110 digital tff files, digital contact sheets, jpeg image files, mp4 video files, and 20 color inkjet photographic prints measuring 20x 24 inches. There are also social media posts (screen shots), logs, scripts, shotlists, and data sheets. Video interviews with several immigrants and one ship staff describe conditions in detention centers in Libya and on board the boats. Also includes scans of 17-page journal kept by Zammit Lupi while aboard the rescue ship.
  Arrangement
  Most of the files and prints are arranged according to the timeline of events as photographed by Zammit Lupi.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Collection contains electronic records that must be requested through the collection guide and accessed in the Rubenstein Library reading room. Note: tiff images are immediately accessible through links in this collection guide.
  Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
  All image titles, captions, and other descriptions have been transcribed from the originals.
  - TIFF images (electronic files), 2017 December 15-19; 110 files (.tif); 11.4 GB
    - At muster station, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0001)
      Crew members of MV Aquarius, a migrant search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, wait at their muster station during a firefighting drill, as the ship makes its way towards the search and rescue zone in the central Mediterranean off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Aquarius fire fighting drill, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0002)
      Crew members of MV Aquarius, a migrant search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, take part in a firefighting drill, as the ship makes its way towards the search and rescue zone in the central Mediterranean off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrants await rescue 1, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0003)
      Migrants on a rubber dinghy await rescue by the crew of MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Rescue at sea 1, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0004)
      Migrants on a rubber dinghy are rescued by the crew of MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Rescue at sea 2, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0005)
    - Rescue at sea 3, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0006)
    - Migrants await rescue 2, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0007)
    - Migrants await rescue 3, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0008)
    - Migrants await rescue 4, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0009)
    - Migrant in rescue RHIB, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0010)
      A migrant sits in a RHIB (rigid hulled inflatable boat) from MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, after being rescued from a rubber dinghy in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrants on Italian RHIB 1, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0011)
      A rescue boat from the Italian Navy frigate Rizzo brings migrants rescued from a rubber dinghy to the MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrant reacts on deck, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0012)
      A migrant reacts on the deck of MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, after being rescued in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrants rest after rescue 1, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0013)
      Migrants rest on MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, after being rescued in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Crew member helps migrant, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0014)
      A crew member helps a migrant on MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, who was rescued in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrant boards Aquarius 1, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0015)
      A migrant rescued from a rubber dinghy is helped aboard the MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrants on Italian RHIB 2, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0016)
    - Migrants embrace, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0017)
      Migrants embrace on the deck of of MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, after being rescued in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrants wait to board Aquarius, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0018)
      Migrants rescued from a rubber dinghy wait to board the MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrant boards Aquarius 2, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0019)
    - Migrant boards Aquarius 3, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0020)
      A migrant rescued from a rubber dinghy is helped aboard the MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017.166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrants rest after rescue 2, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0021)
      Migrants rest on MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, after being rescued in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017.166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrant child brought onto Aquarius, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0022)
      A migrant child is brought aboard MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, after being rescued in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrant child cries, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0023)
      A migrant child cries after being brought aboard MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, after being rescued in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrant boards Aquarius 4, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0024)
    - Migrant boards Aquarius 5, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0025)
    - Migrants queue for registration, 2017 December 15 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0026)
      Migrants queue to be registered on MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, after being rescued in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 15, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrants sleep, 2017 December 16 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0027)
      Migrants sleep on the deck of MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, after being rescued in the central Mediterranean 69 nautical miles off the coast of Libya, December 16, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrants dance 1, 2017 December 16 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0028)
      Migrants dance on the deck of MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, the morning after being rescued in the central Mediterranean off the coast of Libya, December 16, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrants dance 2, 2017 December 16 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0029)
    - Migrants talk 1, 2017 December 16 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0030)
      Migrants talk on the MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, the morning after being rescued in the central Mediterranean off the coast of Libya, December 16, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrants talk 2, 2017 December 16 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0031)
    - Migrants talk 3, 2017 December 16 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0032)
    - Migrant looks out to sea 1, 2017 December 16 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0033)
      A migrant looks out to sea on the MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, the morning after being rescued in the central Mediterranean off the coast of Libya, December 16, 2017. 166 migrants were rescued and brought to the Aquarius in a joint operation with the Italian Navy frigate "Rizzo". Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrant calls out to other migrants, 2017 December 16 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0034)
      A migrant on the MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, calls out to migrants on the MV Open Arms, the search and rescue ship of Proactiva Open Arms, before a mid-sea transfer of migrants in the central Mediterranean off the coast of Libya, December 16, 2017. 154 migrants were transferred to the Aquarius from Open Arms, bringing the total on board to 320. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - RHIB approaches Open Arms, 2017 December 16 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0035)
      A rigid hulled inflatable boat (RHIB) from MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, approaches the MV Open Arms, the search and rescue ship of Proactiva Open Arms, before a mid-sea transfer of migrants in the central Mediterranean off the coast of Libya, December 16, 2017. 154 migrants were transferred to the Aquarius from Open Arms, bringing the total on board to 320. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrants look out to sea 1, 2017 December 16 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0036)
      Migrants look out to sea on the MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, in the central Mediterranean off the coast of Libya, December 16, 2017. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Open Arms RHIB alongside Aquarius, 2017 December 16 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0037)
      A rigid hulled inflatable boat (RHIB) from MV Open Arms, the search and rescue ship of Proactiva Open Arms, arrives alongside the MV Aquarius, a search and rescue ship run in partnership between SOS Méditeranée and Médecins sans Frontières, during a mid-sea transfer of migrants in the central Mediterranean off the coast of Libya, December 16, 2017. 154 migrants were transferred to the Aquarius from Open Arms, bringing the total on board to 320. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Migrants transferred from Open Arms 1, 2017 December 16 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0001, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0038)